all right
hello and welcome everyone it is July 11
2023 we are in active inference for the
social sciences and today is going to be
a lecture by Ben White on basics of
active inference the active inference
agent Subban thank you for the lecture
off to you and we're looking forward to
it
thank you very much yeah me too
um very happy to be a part of this
um to be kicking things off with the the
first module on this course
um I'm going to be talking about
um the active inference agent and trying
to cover some of the basics
um I won't take too long introducing
myself Ava or gave a very thorough
introduction
um in in his talk recently but I'm a
second year PhD student in philosophy at
the University of Sussex and I work with
Andy Clark and with aval and some other
people
um using active inference
to try and find things out about our
relationship with technology and within
the context of well-being and mental
health
the aims for today I'm going to try and
provide quite a wide-ranging overview of
how active inference has connected with
areas of philosophical interest and
particularly how they relate to the
individual agent and the experience of
the agent and how the agent finds
themselves in the world so I've split
this up
um to look at several different defined
topics so I'm going to move quite
quickly through mind agency emotion and
phenomenology and I'm going to say a
little bit about the self as well and
then there's going to be a case study at
the end that I'm going to move through
if we have time
so one of the other aims that I have is
to lay out very clearly some of the Core
Concepts and core mechanisms like
Precision weighting and prediction error
generative models I'm not going to go
into any technical details whatsoever
this is all going to be fairly abstract
my background and my interest in these
Frameworks is philosophical so it's
quite quite abstract in terms of how
everything fits together
and I'm going to try and bring some of
these threads together to to build up a
layered picture of what the active
inference agent is like because this
course is kind of aimed towards seeing
how active influence supplies to larger
scales Collective Behavior social norms
socio-cultural Landscapes and I think in
order to do justice to those things we
need to First have a good idea of the
individual in active influence so we've
got our work cut out for us um so I'll
get started
so before I dive in I wanted to just say
a little bit about how these Frameworks
hang together so
um
active inferences based on call for
instance free energy principle I think
most of us are familiar with that but
it's
the free energy principle just states
that in order to persist Through Time
biological organisms must occupy only
those states that it would expect to
occupy given the type of thing that it
is so free energy is essentially a
measure of the disattunement between a
system and its environment and I'm going
to say say a little bit more about a
tune and how that gets cashed out in
various ways as we go on
active inference is a process theory
that essentially explains how embodied
organisms actually go about remaining in
those expected States so how we actually
go about minimizing free energy and the
idea is that all adaptive behavior is
explained by agents garnering evidence
to confirm
um their own expectations
the predictive processing for the
purposes of the lecture today I'm going
to treat these as synonymous because
most of the work that I kind of came up
through as I was learning about this was
predictive processing and all of the
papers
um that we're using today that refer to
predictive processing refer to a
predictive processing that I take to be
more or less synonymous with active
inference so that's a a very embodied
inactive flavor of predictive processing
I think generally the difference is that
predictive processing can be a much
broader term and predictive processing
can also apply to passive models of
perception but we're not going to
concern ourselves with that
okay
so some key concepts of active inference
slash predictive processing then
so the framework says that agents embody
or agents have
um we won't concern ourselves with the
with the Nuance there but they have a
generative model which is essentially
um a kind of understanding or a model of
the regularities that underpin the
Dynamics between the agent and the
environment so another way to think
about this in very rough terms is a kind
of mental model of the regularities in
the world and how the agent exists in
the world
and using that model the agent can
generate predictions about its own
sensory States so given the model what
kinds of sensory States would it expect
to find itself in in a particular set of
circumstances
and so where those predictions don't
actually match the sensory inputs so
where there's a discrepancy between the
actual income incense data and the
prediction
prediction errors are generated and
prediction errors are going to flow
upwards through the hierarchy so the um
the generative model is said to be a
hierarchical model and predictions flow
downwards some prediction errors flow
upwards and the sole imperative of the
brain body system according to this
framework is to minimize those
prediction errors
so
a good way to kind of get a little
handle on this is to think about just
the example of perception so perception
traditionally so I'm talking about
visual perception here it's
traditionally been understood as a
bottom-up process and what that means is
that the brain waits for incoming
sensory signals and then it processes
them as they come in and it combines
them in kind of increasingly abstract
ways and what we see is some combination
of those sensory signals that have come
in and been processed and combined so if
if you think about me leaving my uh
apartment in the morning and stepping
out onto the street and seeing some cars
what's happening there is some sensory
information is hitting my retina and
it's being processed at first with for
very basic features like light shade
edges and so on and so forth and then
it's being combined with my
understanding of what car is or what a
bus stop is and that gives me my kind of
visual field
predictive processing aimlessly at this
point flips this picture upside down on
its head so visual perception on the
predictive process and is a top-down
Affair so the generative model is going
to encode multi-level expectations about
the likely scene so just to be very
clear when we talk about multi-level and
hierarchical the higher up is the higher
up levels are going to be tracking
longer time scales and higher levels of
abstraction and the lower levels are
going to be much faster and much more
concrete
so a changeable scene so there's going
to be some variation in what I see when
I leave my apartment every day is going
to mean that there's always going to be
some error in that picture so it's never
going to be the same two days in a row
or it's extremely unlikely to be so no
matter how well I can predict what I'm
going to see when I leave my house it's
always going to be cleaned up by some
prediction errors okay so essentially
when I step outside and I step into the
street my brain is already anticipating
what it's going to see out there
okay so I know where particular cars are
going to be parked I know where the bus
stop is so on and so forth and the
perceptual experience that we have is a
construction it's uh we actually
experience the expectation that has been
kind of cleaned up post-prediction error
and there's a little bit of debate there
about exactly what it is that we
experience but um for our purposes today
um we can say that visual perception is
essentially a construction
so on the face of it prediction errors
can be minimized using one of two
strategies and this is going to be
really really important
so we have what I just described there
which is perceptual inference that's
where we revise our predictions to
better fit the evidence so essentially
we update our model to better reflect
the regularities in the environment
or we can engage in active inference
which is where the framework gets its
name from which is where we essentially
make the evidence fit the model okay so
that's where we in some sense update the
world so it conforms to the original
prediction and active inference agents
bring about those expected states by
sampling the world in a biased way so
they have certain expectations and then
we sample the world to confirm the
predictions
and I put perceptual inference there in
scare quotes because
perceptual inference on
um kind of readings of most readings of
active inference just becomes a kind of
action Readiness or as ramstead and
colleagues but a state estimation so
it's just perception and action are just
wrapped up in this continuous loop but
it's really all about the action it's
all really all about bringing about
those expected States and perception is
just kind of in service of that process
and so bruenberg and colleagues refer to
the active inference agent as a crooked
scientist which is uh something I really
like I think that's a very Charming
image so we are scientists that are
engaging in some very dodgy Behavior
because we're not really interested in
uh we're not really interested in having
an accurate model we're more interested
in
um confirming our original predictions
Okay so
that was a very very rapid overview of
some of the Core Concepts and mechanisms
but they're going to crop up
continuously so I think we're going to
get um a much better grasp on them as we
go on in this section I'm going to start
to expand on some of those things that
we've just put on the table and I'm
going to begin to flesh them out in
terms of thinking about how active
inference agents actually exist in the
world
so I should say I put this here to
remind me so those of you who are taking
part in the course
um I'm going to make available a
document with all of the readings that I
firstly all of the readings that I've
used to make these slides and then a
bunch of other readings as well that I
think can be very relevant and um
obviously they're going to be organized
in terms of the structure of this
presentation as well so this is just I
put a little sample up on these slides
but there's going to be much more in the
document
so I think it's always good to start
with some guiding questions
so I've thrown up three here
the first is how does active inference
characterize cognition so we've just
looked at
um predictions and prediction errors but
we're going to expand on that a little
bit and we're going to ask what kinds of
processes does cognition involve how is
cognition related to the material
environment this is going to be
something
um how cognition relates to the
environment that's going to be very
important in subsequent weeks and we're
going to ask quite briefly what kinds of
vehicles might realize cognitive
processing
okay so it is here's a couple of whales
whales are going to be a recurring theme
in this lecture
um but I wanted to take a step back and
ask about Attunement because this is one
of those Concepts that gets thrown
around a lot and I think once it's
grasped it becomes very very clear and
very easy to use but I think prior to it
being grasped it can be a little bit
opaque and a bit slippery so on the left
we have a humpback whale that was found
dead in the Amazon rainforest allegedly
I don't know if this was true and on the
right we have a whale in its natural
environment and I think clearly the
intuition here is that in one case the
whale is very well attuned to its
environment and in the other case it's
not
and I think that we can start by asking
what is it about the ocean that allows
the whale to be well attuned and what I
want to say here is that the particular
Dynamics Between the Ocean and the whale
allow the whale to do certain things
that it can't do when it's in the Amazon
so in other words we might say that the
ocean affords certain things to the
whale specifically filter feeding
um being able to move its vast weight
around with ease
um things that unfortunately are wailing
that Amazon can't do
so affordances are opportunities for
Action
um they they are things roughly speaking
in the environment that the agent can
act upon and there's some debate about
the proper way to really characterize
affordances but I like to think of them
as relational properties emerging from
an environmental feature and some
skilled embodied ability of the agent so
the same thing in the environment will
not afford the same thing to different
organisms so for example uh soil to a
human agent might afford walking on or
laying down on but to an earthworm it
affords very different things and also
even amongst the same organisms with
humans especially different surfaces and
features of the environment will afford
different things depending on your
particular skill set
um and agents are going to go about
minimizing their uncertainty so
minimizing prediction errors staying
attuned to their environment through an
engagement with affordances and this is
going to be something that is going to
drift away slightly as we move through
some sections and then it's going to
come back very heavily at the end
and I should say that the idea of
affordances to my knowledge it first
emerges in the work of James Gibson the
ecological approach to visual perception
I think is chapter eight in that book
that really lays out a theory of
performances
so this idea that systems or organisms
maintain their organization through
ongoing action
um means that active inference has been
labeled as quintessentially inactive by
Corporation and I think that this is a
nice in inactivism is an older framework
from theoretical cognitive science and I
think it's a nice way to understand some
of the key features of active inference
but it does come with a little bit of
historical philosophical baggage and I'm
going to try and unpack that really
quickly
um because I want to unpack exactly what
it is that we're committing ourselves to
when we think about cognition in in
activist terms
so inactivism comes in various strands
very very quickly and roughly you have
Auto poetic inactivism which commits
itself to what's known as the Mind life
continuity thesis this is essentially
that the structures that um give a
ground to life itself are the same
structures that instantiate cognitive
processes
um sensing on this view is teleological
because it's Oriental oriented around
supporting vital systems so things in
the environment have intrinsic meaning
to the organism because they support the
vital
um functioning of the organism in some
way
sensory motor in activism emphasizes how
mobile and embodied agents essentially
enact the grounds and conditions for
their own sensory engagements with the
world so the world is not a kind of
neutral static given that we're
parachuted into actually the conditions
through which we sense the world
are the conditions that we
um we can move and kind of interact with
the world in various ways
um and then there's radical inactivism
and this is
um The View that cognition is purely
grounded in these agent environment
Dynamics it's a purely dynamicist
account of cognition and there's no role
whatsoever for internal representations
so certainly in certain brands of
sensory motor in activism there remains
a role for internal manipulation of
representations and mental
representations are just mental states
that are about something in the world so
some mental state is reconstructing some
feature of the world and this all harks
back to
um kind of old debates in philosophy of
cognitive science between internalist
Notions of cognition and more embodied
embedded extended and will take a more
of a look at that in a second but the
question here is what are we committing
ourselves to with active inference
active inference and I need to be a
little bit careful because I think that
people are going to disagree with this
to a certain extents
but I think we're certainly committing
ourselves to sensory motor in activism I
think that's fairly uncontroversial and
I would say as well that the the
underpinning of active inference by the
free energy principle by my lights also
commits us or it certainly Chimes very
deeply with the core tenets of Auto
poetic inactivism
but I think what's really interesting in
trying to understand cognition in the
active inference agent is to understand
what role if any there are for
representations
so
if you have any familiarity with the
literature on active inference you'll
know that active inference people are
always banging on about models
prediction errors
um various other computationally
sounding things and so the worry here is
at least for
um well it's not necessarily A worry but
the thought the thought would be are we
committing ourselves to a form of
cognitivism and again cognitivism is
this is generally considered to be a
old-fashioned notion of cognition as
like computation over symbolic
representations in the brain According
to some syntactic set of rules or
something
and typically over the last couple of
decades in cognitive science people have
been moving away from that view so it
would be interesting if we were
committing ourselves to something that
we'd already moved away from and some
people think that we we are making that
commitment so Jakob Howie for example
has argued in various places
um that essentially predictive
processing or active inference commits
us to these very rich reconstructive
Notions of representation and even Andy
Clark
um Jacob Howie's Boyle in many many
places has said himself that he thinks
that representations play a role here as
well so in a talk in 2016 Clark said
it's internal representation I think it
is these are representation using
stories but it's not internal
representation in quite the way that we
originally thought about it
so there's some differences perhaps
major differences between Howie and
Clark there but others have pushed back
so there's a paper by Maxwell ramstead
and colleagues from 2020 I think it's a
tale of two densities paper
where they say
um
that a proper understanding of the
generative models in active inference
suggests that there's no role for
representations
um so this is the kind of anti-howie
view
so
I really like this paper from Axel
constant and Andy Clark and Carl friston
which essentially tries to broker some
kind of piece in a debate that in some
form or another has been raging for
decades so it'd be quite nice to finally
put this to bed
um so they argue that we can find in the
formalisms of active inference we can
find grounds for an Armistice here
um so they argue that the formalisms of
active inference show that quote
representational and
non-representational cognitive processes
can be implemented by the brain under
active inference and they do this by
showing that active inference
accommodates a dual architecture
so they show that on the one hand
um in some sense the brain has to
represent because under active inference
uh action selection policies are
happening over extended time scales and
so the agent has to engage in some kind
of counter factual thinking so if I do x
what happens if I do y what happens and
so on and the argument very roughly
speaking is that that is going to entail
some kind of representational some use
of representations
but on the other hand they argue that
what they call diontic actions are
processed through different mappings in
the generative model and they're
directly triggered by sensory input so a
deontic action is an action that is
ingrained by our sense of the
expectations of others so the example
that the authors use is stopping at some
red traffic lights in the middle of the
night when there's nobody else around
so in a sense the the claim is that we
through a kind of social conditioning we
know what the what other people would
expect us to do in those circumstances
and that allows for this kind of dynamic
reflective reflexive
um action policies I think
and in those cases
um there's no room for representer or
there's no need for representations
there
um I would uh definitely suggest people
interested in this go and read this
paper because you might already have
thought you might already have thought
of some potential objections here uh to
the um the claim that representations
aren't needed for the Arctic action and
they do go into some detail in talking
about uh potential objections there
so
that's the kind of status of the role of
representations
um it's a live debate not everybody
agrees but it certainly looks as though
active inference has the formal tools to
accommodate both sides of the debate and
it might turn out that that's a good
thing because we can make everybody
happy or it might turn out to be a bad
thing because you might think well we've
not really settled anything one way or
another
I wanted to take some time though
um to mention
um Extended active inference so I've
been talking about inactivism and I've
mentioned that uh I've mentioned this
debate between cognitivism and older
older ways of thinking about sorry
cognitivism and newer ways of thinking
about cognition as embodied or embedded
and these are part of what's known as
the 4E Paradigm and clearly I think we
are talking about inactive cognition and
you get embodied and embedded kind of
for free with this so the only one left
on the table is the extended mind and
this was just the claim that under some
conditions
um the system that's
um realizing cognitive processing can
literally extend outwards from the mind
so I'll put some nice readings for this
up if anybody's unfamiliar and
interested but it's usually the most
controversial of the four is
um
and Andy Clark who is one of the
original authors of the extended mind
paper really thinks that uh active
influence accommodates uh the extended
mind Theory and it's not just that it
accommodates it but it actually solves
some old problems in the extended mind
about knowing how and why the brain uh
knows when and where to recruit certain
extraneural resources and part of the
argument for this what really sits at
the core is
um Club develops this argument based on
the fact that the generative models in
active inference are always in this
always making a trade-off between
accuracy and complexity so you want your
model of the world to be accurate enough
that you can act effectively on the
world but you also want to minimize the
metabolic costs of having models that
are overly complex and so Clark utilizes
this insight to to make the case that
this explains that in some cases we as
agents we make use of these um extra
neural kind of props and tools and
things
um and he says that the the imperative
to reduce uncertainty provides a
location neutral cost function that's
always been missing from the older
arguments around extended mind
so the upshot to this I think is that
you end up with a view of Agents as
deeply coupled with their environments
so under active inference it's just
nonsensical to try and think about
agents as decoupled from their
environment the generative models
themselves are of the Dynamics between
the agent and the environment so these
two things can't be decoupled
um perception action Loops so remember I
said that perceptual and active
inference are essentially the same thing
they're the part of this circular
causality and they see the agent
constantly producing their own worlds
they occupy the states that they're
expecting to through action
and
we might think based on the literature
that I've gone through that there's some
role here for representations so we're
not committing ourselves
um the active inference agent is not one
that fits with very radical
interpretations of inactivism
um and inact active inference agents are
porous they're open to recruiting
external material features of the
environment to reduce complexity and
therefore minimize the metabolic costs
of realizing those expected States
okay
so that was a bit of um active inference
set against the backdrop of some older
questions in philosophy of mine
theoretical cognitive science but I'm
going to jump straight into agency and
motivation now because there's a lot to
get through here
um I'm going to start with a dark room
problem this is a canonical
philosophical worry in active inference
so a lot of people I think will be
familiar with this and in really brief
terms it's really easy to State
um The Challenge here is to say
if it's all about minimizing prediction
error why don't we just find the most
predictable environments possible and
stay there and live a nice error-free
life
so Andy Clark paints a picture of a dark
room and you can just be strapped up to
a to a intravenous drip feeding you the
nutrients you need and you can just be
really happy
but clearly we don't do that
um active inference or sorry agents in
the world us we uh generally typically
sometimes we do enjoy dark rooms but
most of the time we don't for any
extended period of time and so there's a
challenge here about how active
inference can account for what appear to
be motivated agential actions that
necessarily mean we're confronted with
some degree of uncertainty
um and I'm going to set active inference
up in a kind of dialectic with folk
psychology here because folk psychology
faces No Such concerns
um so to be very clear folk psychology
is just the kind of propositional
linguistic framework that the folk use
to talk about and describe motivated
action so it's a language we typically
use every day to describe the reasons
people are doing things so uh folk
psychology has this belief desire
intention schema where if I want to
explain my friend
um going to grab a beer I would say my
friend believes there's beer in the
fridge my friend desires beer and so
those are combined to form the intention
to go and get beer so folk psychology
doesn't have these kinds of problems
um so just a little bit more on the dark
room problem and another whale
um so the dark room problem invites more
than one answer we're going to see more
than one answer to it as we go along
um one response is to talk about what
drives curiosity and play and
exploration and we're gonna we are gonna
see more of that but the First Response
offered by friston Thornton and Clark is
to highlight the fact that organisms
have basic needs to eat drink and
reproduce what you might call
evolutionarily ingrained needs and that
those needs are going to necessitate
some form of exploratory Behavior so
staying in the dark room will inevitably
under most circumstances going to lead
to physical dissipation
so the question is are these kinds of
appeals enough
and I wanted to pull up a paper by Colin
Klein 2018 that I think is like a really
nice articulation of these challenges
ultimately I think he's wrong and it
falls flat but I think it's a strong
articulation
so Klein argues that predictions alone
simply can't account for the
motivational character of these needs so
Klein says look it's fine that you've
got these needs nobody's going to deny
that but you just have this one
primitive to describe
how those needs motivate you and
prediction is just not going to do it so
prediction alone as your sole primitive
is not going to be able it's like
predicting is not the same thing as
being motivated by something
um and Klein is really not happy with
appeals to these phenotypic needs and he
construes these in the relevance of The
evolutionary history of the organism and
goes into a little bit of detail so he
says look you're right these
expectations are either going to be
about States possible States so the
state of being fed or clothed or warm or
they're going to be about State
transitions about what the appropriate
action is in one state to move to
another state
and he says expectations about States
themselves aren't going to work because
you have this problem of accounting for
novelty so it might be the case that in
my evolutionary past all of my ancestors
have had the same expectations about
which states they're going to occupy but
there are lots of states in my life that
I could be motivated to occupy that
there's simply no evolutionary history
to account for
and he says there's a very similar or a
similarly difficult problem with State
transitions where essentially what we're
talking about with State transitions the
most appropriate actions so I have
expectations about the actions that are
going to fill for that I need to take
under certain circumstances that are
going to get me to a particular expected
State and uh Klein's worry is that
there's just going to be too many
possible actions in any given situation
so there's just a kind of
um a kind of explosion that's just going
to be unaccountable for there's just
going to be too many different ways of
getting to an expected State
um that won't be uh we won't be able to
account for in our past
so it's fairly
robust thorough challenge you've built
on the dark room problem and I think
actually there are it's a worry with two
faces so I think
um the first is about how active
inference can describe agential Behavior
with its ostia purely docsastic
landscape so if you imagine
um somebody looking at their house
burning down it seems like you need more
than beliefs to explain any course of
action they take so there has to be
desire in there somewhere so this is an
example Andy Clark uses in one of his
papers and he says you know um
the desire to run in and rescue some
kind of some item that you want from the
house or the desire to claim on the
insurance is the thing that's going to
dictate how you explain the person's
Behavior so that's the first problem we
need to look at how folk psychology uh
tessellates with uh prediction
and the other problem is maybe a little
bit maybe a little bit deeper and that's
to ask how does active inference
actually account for agential Behavior
so can we even tell some story using
just predictions and prediction error
about what really moves agents to act
so firstly thinking about folk
psychology there's a couple of ways to
go here and I think ultimately we can
answer this worry
so Ryan Smith and colleagues in 2022
um in their paper active inference
models do not contradict folk psychology
they argue that the formalisms of active
inference can accommodate a belief
desire distinction
now I'll admit the that's a very math
heavy paper and it's a little bit beyond
my capabilities but the claim here is
simply that there's no contradiction
that actually the worry that the
important thing we have in folk
psychology is desire and we're not
getting that in active inference this is
just an unfounded worry
but there's another strategy as well so
Joe Dewhurst in his 2017 paper he
employs a different strategy and he says
look what are we even doing with folk
psychology let's not kind of be too
hasty
um and we we need to think about what
are we doing when we talk about these uh
these propositional kind of States
um so he says the first option is to say
well we're just being realists here so
when I say that X desires y I'm actually
positing the real existence of a
fine-grained mental state in ex's head
and he thinks that this is actually the
wrong way to think about things he
thinks that folk psychology actually
it's an instrumentalist tool it's a kind
of framework that we use just for
picking out course grained behavioral
patterns in some useful way
so if we agree with Dewhurst here and we
just become instrumentalists about folk
psychology again it looks as though
there's different um we don't we're not
forced to kind of worry that
um there's some kind of empirical
problem here where the mechanisms of
active inference are in some sense
incommensurable with real properties
that we're positing the existence of
because we're just going to say that
those things don't really exist in the
way that we've typically assumed that
that they might
um so either way
um whichever route you go down here it
looks like active inference agents have
beliefs and that we can we we're going
to be fine in describing motivated
action
so what about the second problem
so Andy Clark in 2020 authored a direct
response decline
um so Clark wants to argue that actually
using predictions and prediction errors
and uh Precision waiting which I'll
explain in a second
um we can get a picture of agential
action
um
so the first thing Clark does is to
outline the fact that under active
inference we have a very nice well-worn
account of embodied action so in other
words what it takes to actually move the
body to perform different actions is
perfectly folded into active inference
under the same kind of computational
flow of prediction error minimization
just in a nutshell for me to move my arm
what I'm doing is making a prediction
that my arm is in some place and then
minimizing the prediction error
um so once that's on the table Clark
says okay that's fine uh we have this
account of action but that's not really
what Klein means
um so the move clock makes is to appeal
to the hierarchical nested structure of
the generative model and to say that
higher level beliefs which are temporal
about temporally extended future States
these are going to perform a really
important role as a kind of controller
for lower level actions so the idea is
that if I have
um a high level temporally extended
expectation to attain a PhD what happens
is that high level belief becomes
unpacked at lower levels in the
hierarchy and what you get are more
fine-grained faster action policies that
the system expects to help support that
higher level expectation
and
there's a mechanism in play here called
Precision weighting which applies to
um prediction error signals because
obviously
um not all of the incoming not all of
the predictions we make about the
environment are going to be equally
important we're not going to have equal
confidence in all of our actions to
bring about an expected State and so
what Precision weighting does is
essentially communicate how much
confidence we have in a particular
action policy to move us into that
expected State under perceptual
inference and precision weighting just
signals how
newsworthy prediction errors are so how
important they are for the system so
Precision weighting drives attention for
example
um when we're talking about predictive
processing but in this case Clark's
claim is that when you have this kind of
nested hierarchy of expectations so you
have temporally extended expectations at
the high level unpacked into a kind of
web of lower level action policies and
precision waiting is kind of modulating
the system's expectations about which of
those policies are most likely to bring
about the expected state
you get something that looks a lot like
motivated directed action and agency is
kind of inherent in this model because
the agent has to the system rather has
to model itself
as a cause of those expected States so
if I if I have these high level
expectations
I in a very inherent way have to model
my own cause or efficacy to bring about
those States so on a very low level the
system has to model some form of agent
because I can be the cause of change to
my own sensory States so I can cover my
own eyes and so on and so forth so kind
of on this view agency is a latent
variable in these systems when it's
making these predictions so it just kind
of turns up and
clock argues that you you essentially
end up with something that looks very
much like
um agents on the folk psychology but he
thinks this is a better view because we
end up with a quote different and
arguably much more unified internal
architecture trading in a single
currency so Clark thinks look okay
Klein's worry is we have this one
primitive we have just prediction and
the concern is that we're not going to
be able to explain agential action but
actually there are ways that we can
appeal to the hierarchical structure of
the model and precision waiting and it
turns out that this is a much more
elegant picture as well
but Klein might press the worry and
anybody listening might kind of think
well
we've kind of done some work there but
why do we expect the things that we
expect in the first place
[Applause]
um
so why is my long-term expectation to
attain a PhD and not to join the French
Foreign Legion for example okay what
means that I expect one thing rather
than another
and here Clark just bites a bullet and
says nobody can explain that what we're
kind of we've kind of shifted to talking
about questions about you know spookier
questions about Free Will and Clark says
look if this is what you want if this is
what you're demanding then you have to
recognize that simply appealing to folk
psychology doesn't get you that either
okay so Klein or you know people
um with these kinds of worries need to
be careful in how much they demand from
the from the active inference agent
and I think the real answer to that
question actually this is more
speculative but the real answer to that
a deeper answer to these kinds of
questions will lie in the kinds of
things that we're going to look at in
subsequent weeks so for example the
reason I want I have the expectation to
attain a PhD rather than join the French
Foreign Legion is because I exist in a
particular kind of socio-cultural
landscape with specific norms and a lot
of my actions and beliefs are tempered
and shaped by the expectations of people
around me
so this is just an overview
we went over the dark room problem
um why do we do anything at all if it's
all about uncertain if it's all about
certainty and prediction error
minimization
um
this worry I said you can kind of
um highlight two aspects of this worry
one is an actual account of agency under
active inference which we have we have
this Andy Clark model of agency to do
with hierarchical nested unfolding
action policies over time and different
precision mappings and then we have this
worry about the relationship with folk
psychology so how do we describe
um agential Behavior motivated Behavior
how do we describe the behavior of
Agents if we only have recourse to uh
prediction
and as we saw there's
um one argument here is that actually
active inference the formalisms can
accommodate this belief desire
distinction and the other move that I
really like is to just say look folk
psychology is just this instrumental
tool it is in effect a kind of it's part
of the socio-cultural landscape that we
use to shape
um each other's Expectations by this
putting these labels to explain our
actions it's a kind of form of active
influence itself
so there's this kind of philosophically
interesting debate about folk psychology
um but we it turns out that everything's
okay and active inference agents are in
fact agents with beliefs desires and
hopes and dreams and so on
okay
that's agency moving we're making good
time
but
okay so in this section I'm going to
introduce quite a lot of stuff
um but it's going to be all tied
together hopefully rather neatly in the
case study at the end I'm going to talk
about allostasis and emotion I'm going
to say very very briefly a little bit
about the self as well
uh here's some examples of some of the
core readings I've used again these are
all going to be up in the document as
well which will be made available
um and I thoroughly advise you to just
have a browse through these there's some
really interesting stuff there
um I'm not going to talk about
um psychedelics or
meditation or depersonalization but
there is some really really cool active
inference literature on those topics as
well particularly papers on psychedelics
and ego dissolution by George Dean but
new paper just came out by
um
Jonas Mago and Robert Carhartt Harris
and I think Fernando Rosas as well I
think I might might be mistaken on the
authors there but it's a very new paper
uh okay so the the thing that is going
to underpin a lot of what I'm now going
to go on to say is going to be this
notion of allostasis
um
and this plays a major role
um in a lot of work on emotion and the
self in active inference Lisa Feldman
Barrett whose theory of emotion we're
going to look at in a second has argued
that the brain's fundamental purpose
what it evolved to do through that
imperative to minimize prediction error
is to manage the body's metabolic budget
so the first prior is uh kind of our
most expected State
um the first prior in the sense of like
our strongest prior
um prior probability our highest
expectation is to have
um good allostatic control and I'm
getting ahead of myself there all that
means is that it's we're balancing our
body's metabolic budgets or like energy
budget in a in an effective way
so
error signals like I said before that
are highly precise are those that are
weighted very highly so prediction error
signals that have high Precision waiting
are the synaptic gain on those error
signals is going to be increased and
that's going to drive learning which
means in future our expectations around
those kinds of error signals is going to
be we're going to pay more attention to
those
um and the most highly weighted error
signals that we're going to get are to
do with our own homeostatic set points
within our own body okay so if my uh
temperature started to rise rapidly my
body temperature started to rise or drop
rapidly
um that prediction error signal those
the violation of those expectations is
really going to grab my attention and
I'm going to do something about it okay
and one way that we maintain these
homeostatic States is through the body's
own autonomic reactions so where I to
start getting very cold
um I would probably start to shiver and
so the body is trying to kind of Rectify
those deviations from homeostatic set
points
but another thing that um organisms
engage in and humans do this to really
remarkable degrees and again this is
going to be something that I suspect is
going to come out in the subsequent
weeks is that we engage in uh quite
complex and sophisticated anticipatory
actions to maintain homeostasis and this
is something called allostasis so
allostatic control which I mentioned
earlier is this first prior is
essentially the regulation of
homeostasis through action so it's
actions that I can take to ensure that I
stay within those important bounds so
shivering is good but living in a house
with central heating is better having a
warm bed and living in a community where
we've had these people of kind of
Engineers have worked to create a kind
of material environment that acts as a
kind of background support to a lot of
these needs
um something that's another important
concept here is allostatic load so this
is essentially the result of not having
good allostatic control so again
allostatic control is just engaging
effectively in actions that are
maintaining those set points whereas
allostatic load is the physiological
costs to the agent of losing that
control so
there's so many studies here that have
um
just shown the immense physiological
costs of operating Beyond those set
points and not having good control so
allostatic load has been linked with
reduced cardiac health sleep problems
um uh gut issues mental health issues
depression uh basically everything it's
really really really bad and so good
allostatic control is very important and
as we're going to see it underpins quite
a few very important things
so
really like we could dedicate a whole
hour to looking at emotion but I'm going
to blast through it very very quickly
right now and this slide I should say
one of the core readings on the document
and the reading that I'm basing this on
is Lisa Feldman Barrett's 2017 paper the
theory of constructed emotion
um
the main idea here is this is a this is
one of those theories that it on the
face of it it seems quite simple but
actually there's quite a lot of subtlety
and Nuance to it
um allostatic control means inferring
the causes of changes to the body's
internal state so in other words if I
want to keep good allostatic control I
need to know what's not just what's
going on out there but I need to know
what's going on inside me as well okay
so if there's some crucial change
happening I need to be on top of it and
this happens through exactly the same
process as the same predictive error
minimization process that I'm engaging
with with the outside world so the brain
is making predictions about its own
internal States and then it's going to
engage in some kind of action to
minimize any prediction errors and these
prediction errors are going to be very
highly weighted they're very important
but here's an interesting thing so there
was a very unethical experiment done by
uh shakhter and singer I think in the
60s who they were emotion researchers
and they conducted an experiment where
they uh injected uh subjects without the
subject's knowledge I think
um they injected them with adrenaline
and then they exposed the subjects to
different uh stimuli so some subjects
were exposed to one type of stimulus and
some subjects were exposed to another
and even though the subjects
had essentially been
um they'd been pushed to have the same
to experience the same physiological
changes in their body they reported
um different emotional like different
kinds of feelings depended on depending
on the stimulus that they'd been exposed
to
so this highlights something really
important and again I feel compelled to
say that I am moving through this
incredibly quickly there's so much to
say here
but the the nub of it is this in order
to keep good allostatic control in order
to know what to do the brain needs to
contextualize those changes in the body
because there's not a one-to-one mapping
between changes in the body and an
external stimulus okay so sometimes
changes physiological changes in our
body are about something in the world
they're a response to something
um and it's very very important that the
brain is kind of taking a Confluence of
those inputs to try and contextualize
okay what's actually happening and what
do I need to do so an example of this is
uh if you imagine running into a bear
while you're hiking in Wyoming which is
something that's actually happened to me
I've experienced it it's terrifying and
you imagine going on a scary or a date
that you're really nervous about
the physiological changes that are
happening in the body are give or take
more or less the same so perspiration
elevated heart rate breathing changes
um so the underlying physiological
footprint is very very very similar but
what you need to do to manage that
situation that apt action is very very
different and so the claim here the kind
of the kind of revolutionary claim in a
way is that emotions
the things we experience subjectively
are constructions just like percepts are
so just like my experience of the car
when I step outside my flat is a
construction that explains away the
prediction error and gives me a cleaned
up picture of the world emotions are
essentially doing the same thing they're
explaining away these prediction errors
and telling me this is the best
explanation of these changes within your
body contextualized against this
external stimulus so in the case of the
date
apt action is to like chill out and be
normal right to a certain extent and in
the case of the bear it's you get the
hell out of that although interestingly
you don't running away from a bear is a
terrible idea
um you should not turn your back and run
away but you get the idea that it's
going to be what you should do in each
situation is completely different
so that's emotion for the active
inference agent it's
and something I don't want to I don't
want to lose here is
what you get with this is really kind of
cool because it turns out emotions and
subjects subject we're kind of moving
into subjectivity here it turns out
emotions are really
um
they're just part of the same cognitive
architecture so there's no difference
here there's no dualism between his
thinking and here's emotion and emotion
is this kind of fuzzy stuff uh that
we're not really interested in actually
emotion subjective embodied feeling is
core it's absolutely vital to
understanding how we
maintain this allostatic control and how
we engage in adaptive behaviors and how
we remain gripped to our affordances in
the environment and the notion of grip
is going to be something that comes up
again very soon
so very very briefly
because this is something that I've
really already talked about but I want
to put a slightly different spin on it
right now
um
I've already said the allostatic control
for humans can involve very very
temporally extended time scales and we
saw this with Andy's model of uh agency
so if you think about something like
saving into a retirement fund for
example okay we're doing something that
the idea is that maybe decades from now
is gonna kind of uh minor spikes in
prediction error called the
disappointment of having not having as
much money right now is going to pay off
later
these are the kind of things that that
humans engage in and our generative
models have to be temporally thick
so that George Dean writes that the
levels of temporal extension are
hierarchically interlocked so shorter
time scales inform expectations of what
the agent can do over longer time scales
so these different levels of the
hierarchy are in a kind of dialogue with
each other telling you what kinds of
things are possible and what kinds of
things you should expect
and when we were talking about agency we
talked about the way that agencies kind
of baked into active inference because
in order for any of this to work the
system has to have as a hypothesis I can
do things okay
um and this is uh more or less taken to
be the same
um the same thing that underpins the
sense of self under active inference so
the system implicitly refer infers its
own ability to bring about intended
sensory consequences and so Dean writes
here quote in Princeton it is in this
sense that implicit in a model of
sampling is a representation or sense of
agency
so
a minimal sense of self it's kind of
like the flip side of agency comes baked
in here so
one has to model oneself as a potential
cause of sensory inputs so George Dean
and colleagues I think George Dean Mark
Miller and Sam Wilkinson propose a model
of the self and the active inference
called the allostatic control model
um and the move they make here is that
we have to recognize that it's not just
our self-efficacy that has to be modeled
we also have to have some kind of idea
in there of how we're actually doing so
we have to model our own capabilities in
order to set Precision waiting on future
action
um so we don't simply infer that we can
be the cause of sensory States but also
infer our own capabilities to
successfully bring about expected States
at longer time scales so the the
phrasing that they use is tracking the
performance or Fitness of the model over
time
so
part of that tracking is going to be
affective and emotional and so there are
strong links we're kind of really
digging our hooks into subjectivity at
this point
but the the claim with the allostatic
control model is you get this rather
than just a minimal self you actually
get a longer term phenomenological self
emerge from these interlocking time
scales which are modeling not only the
system the agent's own causal efficacy
but also modeling how good your own
model is at doing what you need it to do
and like I said I said when I was
talking about the reading I and I want
to flag this again
um because I've really really not doing
Justice
um to this in the way that I should but
this has formed the basis for a lot of
really interesting work on phenomena
like depersonalization
[Music]
um on the role of psychedelics and the
potential for psychedelics in therapy
and in meditation ego dissolution and
kind of um that kind of stuff in in
meditative settings so anybody with any
interest in the self or in those kinds
of practices should definitely go and
give a closer look to these readings
stood up I'll make sure in the document
okay so quick overview here
so active inference agents maintain
homeostasis through anticipatory action
and this is something we call allostatic
control to do this the system must
engage in interceptive prediction over
its own internal States and I actually I
kind of I think I've got time to do this
so I'll just deviate slightly
um the topic of interceptive inference
is really interesting in the context of
active inference so I I want to flag
work by Sarah garfinkel uh who I believe
is at UCL who used to be at Sussex and
um Professor garfinkel's work looks at
um the the central importance of uh
interceptive predictions in various
psychopathologies especially I think
she's looked very closely at PTSD and
anxiety disorders and it turns out that
an agent's accuracy in their
introspective predictions is a good
indicator as to the kinds of symptoms
that they're gonna like the strength and
severity of their symptoms in these
kinds of disorders
um and what she's shown is that if you
can increase the accuracy of
interceptive predictions this forms the
basis of treatment for these symptoms so
in short the better you are at
interceptive predicting I think one of
the measures that they use there in her
lab is how well people can track their
own heartbeats without feeling their
pulse so if you just sit there and try
and say like do do my heart's beating
like this then the more accurate you are
and the more any training you can be
given to be more accurate it forms the
basis of effective treatments for these
kinds of symptoms
um so I just wanted to flag that because
the world of research on in in
interceptive inferences uh large diverse
vibrant super interesting and very much
worth our time
um okay where was I here okay so to to
maintain other static control the system
has to engage in interceptive prediction
over its internal States and then to
best explain changes in those internal
States the system has to contextualize
those changes against some extra
receptive uh input and that's emotion
categories serve that role so just to be
very clear on this view this emotions
are constructions
um there are some important deviations
from other theories of emotion here
um particularly what uh Barrett calls
the basic theory of emotion
um so on her view emotions themselves
have no underlying kind of essence or
neural Footprints and there's a ongoing
live debate there as well between these
theories
and also just at the end
um
the good out of static control in human
agents is this very temporally thick uh
phenomena so we engage in very long-term
planning that involves a lot of the
kinds of counterfactual representations
that we talked about with the actual
constant paper and this has hypothesized
to form the basis of our
phenomenological sense of self
okay
so
okay we're up to an hour
um good we're running on time uh this is
the final section and
um it's probably going to be probably
going to be the longest section what I
want to do here is I want to introduce
um
I want to try and pull together some of
the things I've been talking about
because it's been very fast and very
abstract and I want to try and pull some
of these things together in a slightly
more concrete example so the case study
I'm going to use is addiction so there's
a particular account of addiction in the
predictive process in literature that I
think
in a very succinct Sharp Way highlights
a lot of the things I've been talking
about and puts them within a context
that is quite Stark and easy to
understand
um but in order to do that I'm going to
have to introduce
a new
um slightly more difficult to understand
mechanism within the framework that
crops up in a lot of the predictive
process in literature and what this is
going to do hopefully as well is give us
some a direct bridge to phenomenology so
when we talk about things like neuro
computational phenomenology
um this the things I'm going to be
talking about here have underpinned a
lot of the a lot of the work in that
area
so these are some of the readings we're
going to look at some work by uh mostly
um a lot of the papers we're going to
look at uh first author Mark Miller or
Mark Miller's been the second or third
author and I bring that up because in
the discussion section
um on the 25th when we have an hour to
kind of unpack and answer people's
questions we're actually going to be
joined by Mark Miller so if anybody has
any specific questions about the things
I'm going to talk about now in this
section
um he's going to be the man to answer
those
um but also I'm going to put a lot of
secondary readings up again in the in
the document
um so you'll be able to find them all
there
Okay so
let's suppose switch gears slightly
um
I want to keep the focus on
feelings although what I'm going to be
talking about here are not what might be
called like full-blooded emotion States
um but I want to talk talk about
something a little bit more subtle so
one thing that might seem really really
obvious kind of so obvious that we often
Overlook it when things are going okay
is that it generally feels like
something to be an agent so when we're
going about whatever business we have in
the world
um
we always feel like something
and it's not entirely clear how best to
characterize that so I want to draw on
some work in phenomenology that some
active inference theorists have also
drawn on and made use of because I think
this is a really good grounding for some
of the things I'm going to go on to say
um certainly proved to be a good
grounding for some of the work that I'm
going to highlight
so these are two books by uh
Matthew Ratcliffe who I think is at the
University of York and has done really
really cool work in kind of really
getting to grips with the what it's
likeness to live in certain conditions
and Radcliffe has he argues that he's
identified this certain area uh this
space of feelings that have been largely
neglected in The Wider literature and he
describes these as existential feelings
um so he says
existential feelings are uh quote they
are not intentional States directed at
however many objects and they are not
feelings or of the body or some part of
it instead they amount to a felt sense
of belonging in the world so the main
difference between a full-blooded
emotion State and an existential feeling
is that the emotion state is about
something okay so if I'm uh disgusted
I'm typically well all the time I'm
disgusted about something in the world
okay so emotions are intentional in that
way
um
Radcliffe elaborates on existential
Feelings by
um I'm going to quote this at length
because I quite like it he says
people sometimes talk of feeling alive
dead distance detached dislodged
estranged isolated otherworldly
indifferent to everything
overwhelmed suffocated cut off lost
disconnected out of sorts not oneself
out of touch with things out of it not
quite with it separate in harmony with
things at peace with things there are
reference to feelings of unreality
heightened existence surreality
familiarity unfamiliarity strangeness
isolation emptiness belonging being at
home in the world being at one with
things significance insignificance and
the list goes on
so
this is uh this really really cool work
and I recommend everybody to go and read
Matthew Ratcliffe but um some of the
work I really like in predictive
processing and active inference has
taken this idea of an existential
feeling and what they've recognized is
that these kinds of feelings are really
about how we are orientated in regards
to the world and the affordances in it
so their their background bodily states
of action Readiness so how are we
relating to
um like how do we find ourselves in
relation to the world so we're talking
about the general structuring that's
present in our everyday phenomenology
okay so I really want to make that clear
that what this work is doing is building
a bridge between computational models
and the way even the underpinnings of
those models in neurobiology and
phenomenological experience
so the thing that I need to introduce
and this can be uh it's fairly
straightforward but it can be a little a
little bit tricky at times is this
notion of aerodynamics okay this is
really important so like I just said
aerodynamics is going to provide this
conceptual bridge between different
levels of analysis and it elaborates on
how systems are sensitive to the success
or failure of their own action policies
unfolding across multiple time scales so
the recognition here is that we talk a
lot about action policies and expected
States but the reality is that we have a
multitude of goals and action policies
and expected states that are
interlocking overlapping constantly
shifting okay the picture is messy and
so I like this quote
from the 2019 paper that says the roller
coaster of continual increases and
decreases of errors that accompany life
become expected and are folded into our
expectations for such a system it
becomes important not only to track the
constantly fluctuating instantaneous
errors but also to pay attention to the
Dynamics of error reduction over longer
time scales
so the systems the upshot of this is
that these authors believe building on
some other work in computational
modeling that systems must track the
rate of change in overall error
reduction relative to the system's
expectations so this is
um the kind of global upwards or
downwards Trend in prediction error
that's what the system is sensitive to
sensitive to how that relates to the
expectations
so
the idea here is that aerodynamics
provide a system with a much broader
ongoing sense of how they're doing to
their multitude of goals over time
so
a big step here is that those changes in
the rate of reduction feed back into the
system so they're folded back within the
system and they serve the role of
modulating Precision on action policies
so let's say I'm
engaged in some tasks I have a
particular expectation about how I'm
going to do it that task
and when I actually engage with the task
I do slightly worse than expected
the idea there is that
that rate of change so the rate of error
error reduction is going to decrease
until I'm reducing error worse than my
expectations and in a typical healthily
functioning system that rate of change
the sensitivity to that rate of change
is going to feed back and reset the
Precision waiting on those actions so
it's gonna
reduce my confidence in that particular
action policy such that I might try a
different strategy I might try a
different tactic or I might you know I
might just throw whatever it is that I'm
doing away and go and do something else
so it's we're starting to see this
picture of through expectations
sensitivity to change and feedback onto
Precision waiting it's starting to
dictate how I manage my action policies
so there's this ongoing reciprocal
relationship between aerodynamics and my
future expectations now crucially the
claim here is that on the subject level
all of this manifests as these
existential feelings of some kind so the
way that I feel on a kind of day-to-day
basis is a reflection of how I'm doing
in terms of these sensitivity to
aerodynamics so when I fail at the task
and precision waiting is down regulated
on that particular action policy the
thing that actually that kind of oomph
that moves me to go and do something
else my embodied feelings of frustration
that I experience so our as conscious
agents those embodied feelings are what
are tuning us towards acting more
effectively
so optimal behavior on this account is
characterized as a feeling of a feeling
of grip towards a shifting field of
affordances so I'm going to unpack this
quickly but the feeling of grip in a
nutshell is just this feeling that we're
engaging with our affordances in the
best way that we can and that we're
either meeting or exceeding our
expectations for prediction error
minimization and what they mean by a
field of affordances and this is again
really important
um a landscape of affordances is just
the total opportunities in my niche so
my landscape of affordances right now is
Brighton okay it's not really going to
change very quickly unless I get on a
plane and fly somewhere else
but affordances aren't neutral in that
way they don't just exist there
the affordances that stand out to me as
relevant or attractive
is going to change quite rapidly
depending on what it is I'm doing on my
internal State on the context and so on
so right now my water bottle stands out
as attractive a couple of keys on my
keyboard stand out as attractive but
that's going to shift quite rapidly once
this lecture is over and I turn to do
something else so the idea of grip is
that we are kind of we exhibit a
stability in our Attunement such that we
can remain attuned as that field changes
um and this is part of the skilled
intentionality framework which I I won't
get into because I don't want
theoretical overload but I've put some
papers up on this slide as references
and of course the reading will be in the
document
um but skilled intentionality refers to
the selective openness and
responsiveness to multiple relevant
affordances in a concrete situation so
it's just this recognition that things
change quickly
for multiple reasons and we really need
to exhibit a kind of flexibility and
stability in those engagements
and aerodynamics has been applied in
lots of very very cool ways I can't
recommend this work highly enough
so aerodynamics I won't run through
how everything has been explained just
for time reasons but um you can kind of
take a look at this yourself but
aerodynamics has been proposed as a a
more complete answer to the dark room
problem that we were talking about
earlier because it can explain the drive
for exploration and curiosity because it
literally feels good to minimize
prediction errors better than expected
okay so again that rate of change
manifests as embodied feeling so
um we're always looking for
opportunities to do better than expected
okay and kind of this has been suggested
to account for feelings of boredom
prompting us to go out and find new
things to do and similarly aerodynamics
has provided a computational account of
play which is for a while has remained a
kind of mystery because it's on the face
of it like why would we engage in play
when it's metabolically costly and we
need that energy for other things you
know like Lisa film and Barrett says
like managing energy is super important
so why do baby animals burn it all
engaging in playful Behavior
aerodynamics has a has a story for us
the there and there are also
aerodynamics based accounts of happiness
and well-being and depression as well so
I won't go into the details there but it
turns out that aerodynamics and this
connection to phenomenology is this
super malleable flexible
um kind of uh feature of the framework
that really underpins a lot of what we
experience and do as active inference
agents
okay
so I'm gonna
talk a little bit about addiction
um
got some time here things are going well
so I take
um so so I had some options here because
I wanted to use a case study that really
brought out uh some of the things I was
talking about and as I've just said
aerodynamics has been applied in a bunch
of different areas and it's all very
much worth talking about but I chose
addiction because
uh well as you'll see as I as I kind of
make clear I think it also brings out
not just the way that all of this fits
together but also why it's good
and why seeing people as active
inference agents and broader structures
as active inference structures is
actually a worthwhile thing to do
so addiction was once viewed as a moral
failing
um so the kind of Victorian addict is
too rotten to make the right choice to
self-indulgent
I say Victorian unless you're Peter
Hitchens and then you still subscribe to
this view
um
but that's the old-fashioned view okay
there was something wrong with the
addict some moral or spiritual feeling
and gradually that changed to what the
dominant view is today which is the
disease model
um and the idea here is that addiction
is a disease and that disease is
characterized by
changes in the brain
which changes to brain structures which
mean the addict
um can't help but act in a certain way
when confronted with a certain stimulus
so it's this loss of control that's
engendered through these brain
structures and this is this is the idea
of it being a disease
um
the work that I'm going to describe now
um I won't go into too much detail here
but it's it's it's kind of founded on
this thought that this disease model
can't quite it can't
be quite right because
these changes in brain structure
essentially they like that's what the
brain does like we it's just learning
like this is what we do all the time
like essentially me completing my PhD is
a process of me undergoing changes to my
brain
um such that I'm kind of uh disposed to
act in certain ways
um so there's no so Mark Lewis I think
it's Mark Lewis in his book 2018 the
biology of Desire
um argues look addiction is more of just
a dysfunction in learning it's not
really a disease so we need to think
about it
um a little bit differently and this
work by Miller and colleagues 2020
um that's where it picks up okay so the
idea is that those brain changes
engendered through exposure to a
stimulus in this case we're going to
talk about a drug okay we're going to
leave behavioral addiction aside for a
second
um that clearly plays a critical role
okay so nobody is going to deny
um
the kind of chemical like the role the
importance of the biology here um that's
that's going on in the brain and of
course different drugs have different
chemical profiles in that regard
um but on this view we're going to kind
of shift Focus from that slightly
and we're going to have a much more
active picture where we view addiction
as a self-organizing process of whole
agent environment systems Okay so
um I have this extract here it is in the
dynamic interaction between the agent
and its environment that addiction is
born and endures okay so the harm of
addiction emerges from a breakdown in
the broader stable dynamics that
typically underpin a flourishing life
work family friends health and so on so
these you know typically flourishing
life has a broad kind of bush of
concerns over different time scales in
different areas and what we're going to
see is that the harm of addiction is in
a narrowing of those concerns
so what happens is when somebody
takes a drug
um to some people who are exposed to
drugs that drug is going to through
direct action on some neural mechanisms
is going to signal to the agent that
they've done better than expected at
reducing prediction error of course this
is illusory they haven't really done
better than expected in anything that
matters that the signal they get is wow
like we have just reduced prediction
error at this insane rate
um and repeated use through this
aerodynamics mechanism repeated use is
going to tune our expectations about the
kinds of prediction errors slopes the
kind of slopes of prediction error that
are available to us in the environment
and we're going to start to expect those
vertiginous slopes of error reduction if
we continue to engage with the drug
and once those expectations become
deeply ingrained
um anything else we do is going to start
to feel like failure okay so if I get
used to taking cocaine all the time and
then I have to sit through a family meal
where I don't have any drugs and I have
to kind of sit still and there's no
dopamine available I don't have my phone
that's I'm going to experience that as
feelings of frustration and as if I'm
being prevented from doing something I
want to do and I'm going to experience
that as doing worse than expected okay
so I've learned these expectations for
prediction err minimization and I'm not
getting them unless I engage with the
drug and of course it's worth noting
that in many cases these drugs are going
to have a chemical withdrawal effects
that compound that as well especially
things like nicotine and alcohol in
particular is very nasty so alcohol can
kill you if you uh if you try and
withdraw from it too quickly so they
really do pull the agent into grip
so what happens here is the agent
develops a kind of sub-optimal grip so
you start to enact a new world a new
identity so instead of doing all the
things you once cared about like
different Hobbies you start to hang out
with different people you start to
frequent different places like a
dealer's House or wherever and very
slowly you start to carve out
essentially a niche the addict enacts a
particular Niche through their actions
and they have quite a good grip on that
Niche it's just that it doesn't speak to
a broader array of concerns
so
what's really important is that this is
not this pushes back against a disease
model because on this view the active
inference agent the well the system is
doing essentially what it was evolved to
do so
um there's another quote from the paper
here that I like that says their habits
allow them to remain well attuned
and keep prediction errors under tight
control so long as they remain within
the narrow confines of such a niche so
it's not the and this is important
because it shows that allostatic control
and prediction error minimization are
not the same thing they come apart and
this really it speaks to a question that
was asked after Abel's session recently
um
about what this prediction error
actually look like well in this case you
you have a system that has learned the
engagement with certain affordances
gives it it's an illusion but it has
this feedback that says this is you know
this is the state you expect to occupy
oh this is a state that has the agent
has learned to expect to occupy and it's
carved out a niche of affordances that
means it's very likely to occupy that
state so it actually has a really good
grip on the situation it's just that
um that Niche is very narrow and it's
constricted meaning
um it's simply
that kind of uh
those habits and that web of Habitual
action policies are just not well suited
um to maintained good allostatic control
so everything else in the Alex Life
Starts to suffer
so we can kind of think of this as a
form of Niche construction gone wrong
and I think we're going to look at Niche
Construction in the in the coming weeks
as well
um
so why is this whole agent well so I
should say just to back up a second so
this is
what I like about this account of
addiction is that it's a thoroughly an
active account of addiction it really
brings out the kind of inactive core of
active inference so the addict is
addiction becomes an identity it becomes
a world that the person actually
produces through their actions so rather
than the disease model where you have a
person and a stimulus and exposure you
know whenever they're exposed to that
stimulus they're going to have problems
because of these brain changes what this
does Justice do is actually the activity
of the agent so they're not accidentally
bumping into this stimulus and the
environment they're Del and they're not
just seeking it out but they're
deliberately restructuring their
environment to make this state more and
more likely over time
so it really does does Justice to the
efficacy and the agency of the agent
rather than
giving that agency a more backseat role
that it takes in the disease model
but the other thing that it does because
it's this inactive uh picture is that it
also does Justice to the environmental
features so it also
um it kind of speaks to the fact that
addiction is not just all in the head
actually the real
um some of the problems of Addiction
come with the fact that it is this
um procedural constructive process and
one of my favorite experiments of all
time is um I don't know if people are
familiar with the Rat City experiments
this is why I've got the image up here
and this is a very cool experiment where
originally it was found that if you
exposed rats to a drug-laced stimulus
and environment I think it was um
I think it was heroin laced water or it
might have been cocaine um but the
original experiments found that like
nearly all the rats would kill
themselves with the drug so they would
just keep keep keep at the drug until
um until they died and it was a very
very very high percentage of the rats
would engage in that destructive
behavior until the experiments were
re-run
um sometime later and instead of having
the wrap just in a boring cage on its
own it had the rats in Rat Park which
was a very social exciting brightly
colored environment with lots of
different affordances and what they
found was that given the same Choice A
vastly reduced proportion of the rats
would choose to engage with the drug
okay so it's capturing the importance of
Niche construction that I think is
really nice here and it also speaks to
the role played by embodied affect in
phenomenology there's something that
it's like to be an addict and that
really matters okay it really matters
that the addict has these embodied
experiences when they're engaging with
particular sets of affordances
so that's really summed up in the
overview that I've put here so these
were the things that I wanted to
emphasize
um active inference agents are embodied
they're embedded in a landscape that
landscape is constituted by particular
affordances and we can distinguish
between a landscape of affordances and a
field of affordances and that
distinction really speaks to the
inherent affectivity and normativity of
affordances okay this which affordances
stand out to a certain particular time
which exit a pull over us
um an active inference agents enact
their worlds through action and this is
nowhere stalker than in the case of
addiction
um
active inference agents are effective so
emotion plays this super crucial role
keeping is keeping us tuned keeping us
in that uh grip with our affordances and
helping us contextualize those important
physiological changes
um active inference agents are agents
okay so we do have a way to describe
Behavior as agential and motivated and
we do have these cognitive architectures
that can make sense of agential action
and active inference agents have this
inbuilt sense of self that comes with
agency as well
so that's pretty much it this final
slide just goes over some of the things
that we can expect so this what I've
done today I hope has laid a good
groundwork and has installed some higher
level expectations to learn more about
active inference and what we're going to
do in the subsequent weeks is now scale
this up to see how when you have more
than one active inference agent together
how the expectations of some can impact
the expectations of others and
individuals and I look forward to
to learn more about that but as for me
uh that's it
Amazing Ben awesome work
what can people look forward to next
week or in two weeks if they join the
discussions section like what's it going
to be like or who would you encourage to
join
um I would definitely I mean the more
people that come along I think the
better it's going to be I'm really
looking forward to it I'm I'm kind of
just in the first place Intrigue to see
that we we covered so much ground I'm
just interested to see where people want
to go with this and see where people's
interests lie
um I assume that the people are going to
have questions and I think maybe the
best way to do it would be to explore
some of people's questions during the
discussion we can use them to kick
things off and keep things going and but
I think it's likely that that disco we
we have a whole hour so we've certainly
got time to really dig into things in
some detail and like I said before we're
going to have Mark Miller with us and
Mark is just awesome in discussion it's
very very passionate and enthusiastic
about his work and he can do a much
better job than I can in explaining it
so I just um just to have the
opportunity to speak with Mark about his
work I would I would say definitely come
along
all right anything else otherwise again
awesome job
uh no I think that's it cool thanks for
listening I guess well thanks it was a
pleasure it was ambitious to to what you
did elegantly with no equations
or getting snagged on any of the
potentially infinite philosophical and
uh tactical and normative and all these
different layers of Challenge and
diversions so to really
um to really cut a path there is great
yeah I think it just speaks to there's
there's so much good philosophical work
in these areas in active influence and
predictive processing and I should say
again I mean I I we didn't really do
justice to any of the work I talked
about so that's the final thing I would
say is definitely you know the the
document is there with the reading and
please go and um actually look at the
work of these people because it's it's
something that's really really good
all right
till next time cool thank you very much